another day another scary study keeping
us up at night it's annoying especially
considering that I check under the bed
and in the closet every night not to
mention I sleep with my favorite stuffed
animal to protect me from scary signs
but alas here we are there's a new study
making the rounds indicating that
fasting and not even severe fasting but
intermittent fasting leads to hair loss
or at least that's what the news
articles say like this one and this this
one and this one you get the picture so
is there any truth to it well the study
is very much real and hot off the press
and in this study they did extensive
research into the topic including many
mice but before you breathe a sigh of
relief thinking oh another mouse study
I'm good I did the exact same thing
until I get to supplemental figure 7
because the researchers buried a
randomized control trial under piles of
mouse data never thought I'd say that so
how about we uh skip the mouse work and
go straight to the human data okay the
researchers split people into three
groups one group maintained a normal
weight maintenance diet the second group
used a modest 18-hour fast to 6our
feeding window but also aimed for a
weight maintenance diet then the fin
final group was a calorie deficit with
no fasting so we can see the layout of
the eating times colored in this chart
everything in white is the non-eating
windows so the only differences are the
eating times at least that's the
Assumption so we can verify that by
looking at the average intake on the
left here and the body weight changes on
the right the Orange is the control and
the intermittent fasting is the light
blue box the TRD condition as we can see
they're on par with the control
condition indicating that they may have
been
fasting but they were eating enough
during the 6 hours to maintain their
weight unlike the designed calorie
restriction diet on the far right the ER
condition okay so the researchers had
participants on each of these diets but
at the beginning of the study they
shaved a section of their scalp and then
measured hair regrowth over time and
what did they find well let's look at
the hair regrowth again the intermittent
fasting condition is in the middle if
there's an asterisk above it that
indicates a statistically significant
effect as we see there were no
differences between the normal diet and
the calorie restricted non-fasting
condition but there was a reduced hair
growth in the people using a caloric
maintenance intermittent fasting
nutrition so the news articles weren't
making it up but is there more to the
story well I think so if we look at
different size hairs and the actual
density of the hair shafts on the scalp
here we see there are no differences
between the groups so these data
indicate that hair regrowth is slower
but the density of the hair is unchanged
so to me
this is just telling me that your hair
will grow more slowly but that doesn't
necessarily mean that you'll lose hair
or the number of hairs themselves now
there are some additional nuances here
one the human study lasted something
like two weeks no actually I think like
11 days ultimately while this does
inform on the growth rate I'd really
like to see some long-term data
indicating an actual reduction in the
thickness of hair once hair is
supposedly regrown to a previous hair
length for really striking results check
out one poignant datm from the mice on
the far left the mice are shaved butt
necked and as time passes as we move to
the right Al is the non-fasting mice the
control mice then each condition on the
left is a different severity of fasting
from 21 hours fasting to 19 hours to 16
hours to 12 hours I'll go ahead and tell
you that the mice were still eating the
same amount and the exact same food but
as we can see there's a stepwise
reduction in hair regrowth rate in line
with the severity of the fast in
addition there's more data that the
researchers get into using mice that
indicates some worry if we replicated it
in humans now to be clear as we long
know it isn't a one one comparison to
look at mice and apply to humans in
addition especially from a Time
component an 18-hour fast in a mouse is
a drastically different from an 18-hour
fast in humans that would be equivalent
if we were to try a ridiculous
equivalency game to several days fasting
if not more for a human I imagine one's
hair might not be too Keen to be grown
back quickly if they ate once every
several days or possibly once per week
anyway the researchers put a lot of work
into this and describe the mechanisms
that they believe cause this in detail
which I'll cover in the extended version
of this video that you're watching if
you're interested it's included for the
physionic Insiders along with all of my
other work it's linked in the
description as it stands though my
takeaway is we're making too big a deal
about this at this point in humans
there's only proof of slowed hair
regrowth from a very short study
including men and women but there's
still no evidence of a longlasting or
actual loss of hair thickness effect so
if you're extremely cautious about your
head hair you'll want to avoid intermit
fasting but otherwise I don't see enough
reason to be overly worried here until
we receive more evidence if you're not
watching my breakdown of the mechanisms
Through The Insider version of this
video then I'd invite you to check out
my other publicly available work right
here see you there